Alene Stern Erlanger Papers, 1942-1969
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Alene Stern Erlanger papers
1942-1969
Erlanger, Alene
MS 56 UUID:afcd6d5b-014d-4999-abb6-4baeeb6463d2
1 box (.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Dog trainer and breeder. Small collection of material from Erlanger's work with war dogs during World War II, including correspondence, photographs, citations, and books on dog training.
Alene Stern Erlanger graduated from Barnard College in 1912. She was captain of the Red Cross at Fort Monmouth (New Jersey) during World War I, and between the wars, she directed the Cellar Players, Hudson Guild, an amateur theatrical company. During the Second World War she organized Dogs for Defense, which arranged for the donation of dogs for military service and placed them in homes after the war. As a civilian consultant to the Quartermaster General, 1942-45, Erlanger helped found the K-9 corps, wrote training manuals, and supervised dog training programs. She was awarded the "Exceptional Civilian Service Award" in 1945. She was married to Milton Erlanger and had they three children. She was a well-known breeder of poodles and owned Pillicoc Kennels, Woodside Stud Stables, and a large aviary. Erlanger was considered one of world's leading judges of dogs of all breeds and was the author of Pet Poodle, a manual (1954). She was treasurer of the International Council on Bird Preservation and active in other conservation groups. Alene Erlanger died on June 26, 1969.
For more on Alene Erlanger's contributions to the k-9 corps, see http://www.poodlehistory.org/PoodlesinWWII.HTM
This small collection of material documents Alene Erlanger's work with war dogs during World War II and includes correspondence, photographs, citations, memorabilia, and books on dog training. There is one photograph of Erlanger with actress Greer Garson and her two standard poodles.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Search Terms
World War, 1939-1945--Dogs; Dogs--War use--History; World War, 1939-1945--Women; Erlanger, Alene Stern, d. 1969; Garson, Greer, 1908- --Photograph
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Murray D. Van Wagoner, Governor of Michigan (invitation to dog show), 1942 (Box 1)
  - Henri Bonnet, Ambassador of France (in French), 1948 (Box 1)
  - Yale U. Library (for gift of Joyce manuscript), 1964 (Box 1)
- NY Times obituary, 1969 (Box 1)
- Photograph: Erlanger with Greer Garson and two standard poodles, circa 1942 (Box 1)
- Cartoon from the N.Y. Tribune re: war dogs, 1942, [photocopy-original in flat file] (Box 1)
- Cover of Pathfinder magazine with photo of Erlanger receiving medal and citation for her work with K-9 corps, undated (Box 1)
- Medals and citation for war work, undated, [see also oversized materials] (Box 1)
- Books
  - Technical Manual: War Dogs, War Department, 1943 (no author listed - Erlanger?) (Box 1)
  - Dogs for Defense: American Dogs in the Second World War, by Fairfax Downey, 1955 (Box 1)
- Oversized Materials
  - Original cartoon from the N.Y. Tribune re: war dogs, 1942 (Map-case Flat File)
  - Citation for war work, undated (Map-case Flat File)